so I thought of talking about the um
well in relation to the previous talks
and the mind and the wild animal
series um the first three
fets and the
animal how does it relate to it
so I guess we
can let's take silat
parasa what would
be see about
parasa from your point of view in terms
of
the chetah the wild animal that's
chetah the wild animal that's
there why is it a feta
or rather describe the
F in this
context of the similar we've been
using lots of
times is the animal fed
fed
yeah you are not
seeing the extent to which it's being
agitated I don't mean gen General is the
animal F I mean specifically is the
animal fed
by so you're not
seeing the it being agitated by you
doing some practice acting out of a
sense of Duty or a sense
of doing virtue right but wouldn't that
be wouldn't be right to say then you're
fed one you def fed one cuz you're the
one possessing over and not seeing it
rightly
yeah so which one is
that the
you it would be closer to say you
but I mean what I was thinking um to say
it's not was that um it would be kind of
akin to in the terms of the simile sort
simile sort
of just having
a like you know okay in theory I need to
tame this
animal and but you don't see the animal you
and but you don't see the animal you
don't know how to relate to it you don't
have any and so you just have and all
you can do is have some kind of you try
this like some some kind of set of
instruction and now if I follow these
things I hope that it will count the
animal down
basically so see at that
stage why are you not seeing the
animal precisely because of
expecting the result of peace or something to come
the result of peace or something to come
out of following some kind of prescribed
things so it's in other words your
thought of what the animal is is like
going to be on the other end of when I
finish doing all of these motions or and
who are you doing those motions for then
if the animal is not seen who are you
doing the the duty in the precepts
for s for yourself yeah
that's why the animal is not seen you're
not even paying attention to it in other
words you're doing it out of your
craving your pressure animal a second
you want to First satisfy this this
discomfort of course animal is related
to that internally but you are basically
running past it and doing all these
things just to appease yourself your own
craving your own insecurity your own
doubt and that's why the animal is not even
and that's why the animal is not even
seen intentionally just no no this is
more important for
me and that's why people would struggle
to give up silat parasa it's not oh
thank you wow it was just like a
intellectual mistake no it's you're
doing it because you're obviously doing
it for yourself in the sense of you're
finding some sense of safety some sense
of clarity some sense of method that I
can adhere to without having to Dy
ambiguity everything else is
second and that's the message you convey
to the
animal that well you are not
important and that's why it's your
burden that's why it's your fatter you
the fatter
one so that's that whole point of you
know they we been saying so many
times that you have to
um kind of go against yourself and your
own sort of
u a degree of your own inclinations like
you take on the Priestess but then you
you want overly Define him it's like
well no actually now that's a
problem that will make things
worse needing to to overly Define to
specify to avoid theorizing to to to
clarify to rehash millions of times oh
but the tradition the way the duty the
aent the teacher said this it's like
well yes you need to learn what the
rules are you need to learn what the
extent of um virtue to be developed is
but once you do that then basically now
you actually need to start catching your
own your own self when you're trying to
overdo it overly Define it just to get
the extra sense of safety because more
is
better but it's not more is Tighter and
tight is not
better that's like in that Q&A Poland we
did when I was asking people like would
you eat at 12:15 if you didn't eat the
meal like what's the problem why would
you stop at 120 cuz that's not the rule
would have never said that said stop by
noon noon well when it's the highest
which means it's always going to be a
matter of guess of a guess but the
problem with that is I if I don't decide
on 1200 and I just use that General
sense of is it the noon now well it's
kind of close should I eat should I not
you start second guessing you start
checking your reasons why would you eat
do are you am I really hungry all these
things would be now revolving and you
would have to deal with them you would
have to bear them deal with them make a
decision and then live with the
decision all of that it's actually
closer now to talking into your mind
rightly then if you were to just no no
no
120 that's the time of
Purity and uh I can eat at 11:55 like a
pig shove things down my throat no think
about why I eat how much I eat do I need
to eat all of it and I don't need to cuz
as long as I stop before 1200 I am
pure factually I am blameless
because I did not cross a second past
the noon and you see how ridiculous their
noon and you see how ridiculous their
view
is and people won't give it up because
it offers Clarity and safety and almost
righteousness sense of righteousness as
well just because the animal is not it's
almost like you just sort of I don't
know T put it away in a cage so that you
don't get to see it basically so you
don't have to deal with it
but the whole see how that reinforces
then the view that the Purity comes out
of these random
observances like 11:55 is pure 12000
it's not
pure 1205 you might as well dis robe and
go and get married I mean like there is
no virtue for
you no it becomes very
irrational and um and fing like it's not
going to be just a um as I said a simple
question of correcting the
misinformation for that person to or
drop it no no no they're going to now
have to feel the weight of that
insecurity that they've been running
away from by jumping into these overly
defined um observances basically they're not
um observances basically they're not
even
rules just for the sake of avoiding
ambiguity doubt second guess
reflection all things that pertain to
the mind to the
animal but if you allow those things to
come then basically you start keeping
the precepts for the
animal for the Revelation clarification
containment of the animal and then you
are unburdened
completely you're not fatted you don't
have to do anything for yourself do
anything exactly he just abstaining from
doing these things and and animals
closer and closer and clearer and
clearer and I guess you can see how that
relates to the fact of
Doubt when doubt is present what would
that person
do well it be the same kind of procedure
in terms of um like let me find an
answer to this let me kind kind of
clarify it let me just for the sake of
you know and and it's exactly the same
principle like you keep yourself within
that principle by expecting the piece or
the kind of resolution to come from me
getting the answer to it from the letter
of the text from the external from some
external something
anything so basically you would be again
looking past the animal intentionally to
to basically as I said appease your own
craving insecurity and not even want to
deal with with the
doubt cuz it's too
pressuring that's why I like it's kind
of
funny you know somebody would be doing
all of these things and actually kind of
feeling you know oh but I feel you see
there's no problem like I do all these
things and then I'm kind of at peace and
you know I have all my ways of dealing
with things you start like not doing
them feels like you've taken like 10
steps backwards well because actually
you only just started yeah yeah there
was and you become very dependent on
those circumstances on those highly
managed circumstance I mean there there
were monks that dis
robed so they forsaken the entire
training because they ended up in the
environment where nobody would offer the
food properly you know
traditionally and it's like you realize
like wow how deluded you would have been
all the time to not even realize
important as important and unimportant
as unimportant to not be able to
distinguish so in their eyes it was
better to forsake the entire practice of
freeing yourself from
samsara than
to endure their own misconceived ideal
of Purity I impurity oh but
but I'll go to hell because cuz you know
I'm I'm I can't keep these
technicalities I'm not that I'm not pure
that's I shouldn't do it but you won't
go to hell you know commit into
sensuality and basically following your
senses like an animal no that that that
that will not take you to hell at
all because it's easier because you
still don't take on responsibility see
even when they drro they wouldn't have
taken on responsibility for doing it it
would have been well because you know
the Purity oh okay okay fine fair enough
fair enough
so it's like I just did it because of
this and this was done because of this
and this was done because of this thus
please don't put any of that weight on
me not having to have the burden of
making a choice and really feeling like
what I'm going to do is going to Bear
consequences so how does it relate to
then so you're not
seeing the mind in these two examples
and you're intentionally going past
it and you intentionally refuse to
basically look in this
direction you you you do not want to
take your eyes
from the external sense of Duty sense of
methods sense of
performances sense
of blind adherence to The Virtue and and
and as I said the sense of Duty that
defines you
and same um to that external sense of um
external things that you'll be seeking
to appease your own doubt like because
see the resolution comes from
outside when I get the right information
then doubt cannot arise anymore until it
does which case I need to update my
information and so on and so forth
forth
so why is that rather the third factor
with those
two so why does looking past the
in the sense we just
described why is
that cause I suppose would like a better
word atada why is that the cause of
atada I'm trying to give me an answer
but look at the space in
between remember how you look used to
look past
it what does that
cause okay so what is at let's put it
that way it's translated as belief
way it's translated as belief
inself but it's obviously a bit other
than just believing in
yourself what is the
main defining characteristic
ofada external external and that's what
it has in common it's like by depending
on uh external like Duty Authority is
the external it's a complete assumption yeah
external it's a complete assumption yeah
like the
external resolution to the doubts
external resolution to the doubt
external methods independent of me my
intention my effort my reflection my
responsibility which is how you keep
your sense of self independent yeah but
before that before you even took on
these duties and try to
practice again sense objects dependence
on sense objects desire Delight in sense
objects being defined by possessions
everything external external external
external so your sense of self exists
now on account of the Assumption of that
external I independent of me independent
of my experience as a whole independent
of the five Aggregates and you're
reinforcing that assumption well you
were reinforcing that assumption through
uh um non virtue non-restraint
sensuality but now you are not removing
that assumption either because of your
practice is the practice of silat parasa
and avoiding of the doubt trying to get
rid of it so you are still very much
reinforcing the same thing so goes hand
in hand with
it what you say actually in a way I mean
that's why it's like I don't remember
which s it says but it's like
there you know a baby doesn't think
about Duty or about doubt or whatever
and same sense like somebody who's just
you know normal sensuality not
practicing doesn't necessarily think you
know it wouldn't kind of come up this
you know but but it's like this tendency
that can
only it is it is there it's underlying
of course if you were to try to go
against the sensuality that's and wake
up that's the first thing you're going
to encounter that's you're going to see
what was fing you which is going to be
that dependence on that as I said
external definition for what the truth
is in the sense of to to alleviate the
doubt information and so on the external
weight of the authority of tradition
Dharma sutas doesn't matter but I'll
adhere to
this as a method as a prescribed steps
virtue and Duty basically and same I'm
keeping the virtue for the same out of
the same attitude I'm virtuous because
that will somehow magically in
return do this work for me on the inside
that I'm very much intentionally
refusing to look
at so say then
somebody's becoming aware of this and
then when they have doubt pressure in
their mind they don't just automatically go
mind they don't just automatically go
out and seek the
resolution they endured it they don't a
out of it
they learn to come within that not at
the expense of
it same in terms of
the um that sense of Duty and
virtue they still keep it obviously you
don't go against
it but then you don't well you take
responsibility for doing
so so if you you start shifting that
emphasis on like no no no it's
things are UNH wholesome because they're
rooted in un wholesome intentions and
things are wholesome because they're
rooted in wholesome
intentions and that something that needs
to be repeated reflected upon and and
drilled into it so that you stop
automatically just falling onto the the
Assumption of the external Duty
resolution Authority method weight
removal safety
so say personality endures the doubt
rightly takes on weight of of
responsibility they not just doing it
blindly um to appease their own ideal
and desire
desire
um and then
exactly the signs of the mind would be
more and more apparent the space in
between as a real entity as a real
phenomenon as something that you just
completely looking past looking
through let's say that
way how does that then free free you
from those
feets I mean we said why it would free
you from the F of
Duty because you're not doing it as I
said out of that ideal
that inherently wants avoidance of
responsibility and wants things to come
externally on account of me just going
through the motions do what I'm told
don't be left alone think for myself
that's too much so obviously once you
start seeing the mind you realize that
no this is supposed to be outlining this
has nothing to do with me so you're
relieved of the
duty you're relieved of that entire
burden you're
unfed doubt how how would it relieve you of
doubt how how would it relieve you of
the burden and the factor of Doubt
seeing your
mind it Rel relieves you of the burden
of having to do anything on account of
the doubt no you never had to do but you
don't see that yeah that was your F of
Duty okay so now you don't have to do
anything that's your F Duty gone but now
the F of
doubt you might not be doing anything on
account of
it but it's still there unpleasant fing
you how would you be
unfettered or rather how does seeing
your mind seeing the wild animal how
does that unet you from the burden of
the doubt you you don't doubt
anymore what my describing be the like
the deactivation
of of what what is being
deactivated there're only two options so
which one is
it it is f no that's the point when the
animal comes down within the doubt yeah
you realize that's what the doubt was it
was not the uncertainty it was the agit
of the animal that you were
fueling through constantly seeking the
resolution externally and not allowing
the containment and if you calm the animal
containment and if you calm the animal
within the doubt sufficient amount of
times that doubt part of the uncertainty
the pressure the pain is gone completely
because it was solely because of the
agitated animal and then you realize oh yeah I
animal and then you realize oh yeah I
still have uncertainty but there is no
more doubt and certainly there is no
more view now
that it will come through resolution of
the of the external kind of information
and permutation and so
on so obviously you can't just
deactivate it at at that stage and tell
it to to to calm down you have to
confine it within the
doubt and that that becomes your mode of
being until the animal comes down within
it and then you see what
left and you see what was
gone and that's not that goes hand in
hand with that safety as well that you
would be that's what the first three factors
be that's what the first three factors
go away
together not first and then second and
then there what I was thinking it's kind
of really more like the yeah it's the
same yeah the three implications of the
same thing the safety you find in the
external sense of Duty definition
Authority methods
the safety that then shelters you from
doubt and when doubt comes you basically
fight the doubt by clarifying your
external safety even more and all of
that just reinforces your assumption of
the external as where the sense of
yourself is independent of your
experience even if you don't think
myself is external simply depending on
the Assumption of that degree of
external that is what yourself is
so by by in order for the mind to come
down within that yeah well you have to
confine it within that and not take out
of
that and that's that I think there's
like a
Zen I wasn't a cone it was saying or
something when when like when he start he says
when when like when he start he says
before the practice this monk wrote that
says before the
practice mountains were mountains
forests were forests Rivers were Rivers
something like that when he started
practicing mountains were not mountains
and Forest were not forest and rivers
were not Rivers he was like just
everything top top to bottom was
infected affected by that doubt but then
after his mind calm down the forest were
forest mountain mountain rivers
rivers but you had to go through that
withrawal
basically so now let's say
the animal has been sufficiently tained
so the
first the
fuel for the first three
FS has become redundant basically you're
incapable of fueling it
you're you're incapable of finding
safety there's no need for
safety so all of your previous efforts
would be meaningless now you couldn't
even conceive to assume again what you
have kind of unassumed what you've seen
through so how would then
um what would then be um again in
relation to the animal the removal of
the other two cor of fs sensuality and
well how would you describe that from
the point of view of the of the
chitt I say just to compare it with what
you just um described in terms of doubt
mhm like you would be within the FED of
Doubt um you would be
doubting uh with uncertainty for as long
as you kind
of immediately jump onto as soon as
there's uncertainty I must I must resolve it in
uncertainty I must I must resolve it in
other words the uncertainty becomes
doubt when you kind of go and resolve it
with something external MH and you fail
to see that the whole kind of pressure
of of the uncertainty that makes it into
doubt is the animal
that is like agitated
agitated and when that and when you kind
of realize wait know that that is the
problem the animal calms down it becomes
impossible to do the same so let's say
in terms of sensuality or ill
will it would be the same principle like
you would be having the fet or the
sensuality is there for as long as like
the let's say Prospect of of pleasure
from sight sound smells tast touches
M
implies the resolution of that pressure through
the resolution of that pressure through
going and getting those sight sound
smells St touches and
you and what is like the truth in that
case is that
the the the pressure or the burden the
reason that it's pressuring the prospect
of s most searches is again the agitated
animal that is like delighting mhm
um
so and if the animal were to come down
sufficiently like
thoroughly see the animal can calm down
but that doesn't necessarily immediately
free you from the fet that's my point so
I'm this is my question to myself you
you need to really kind of so well let's
start like this like as as when I was
saying about the virtue Beauty said when
I was asking who who do you do it
for is it you or the animal well the
same question then comes to cality and
your will are you still on the level of
wanting it
yourself are you still on the level of
hating it
yourself or no you don't really want it but you
or no you don't really want it but you
can't help be pressured towards it
I I don't really hate but I can't help
but be pressured by the thoughts towards
it so if it's the second one
mhm well the second one would be if you
would have undone the first
one yeah so first you need to yourself
stop wanting it
like no I generally don't want
this but I can't help it let's put it
that way of course you're helping it in
terms of not acting out of it but I
can't help but have the
desire that's when you can start to
differentiate aha okay so it's that's
the animal's desire it's the animal's
preference and yes for as long as that
animal still will have even possibility
of such desires I'm liable to act out
even if I don't want it so you were
doing it for yourself by not seeing
where the problem was basically
okay then you can make that distinction
well yeah so then those sutas when the
Buddha says like oh yes I I
saw how little satisfaction how perilous
sensuality is how much better
renunciation is but my mind didn't want
to LEAP towards renunciation it still
wanted sensuality so it's like I did everything
sensuality so it's like I did everything
right I have not no it's not that I was
not seeing the paril but the mind was
still wanting it and it was not
accepting the the terms of renunciation
I like oh why is that oh well because I
haven't made
it clear to it basically the
gratification dang Escape so you need to
now stop what we spoke in previous
talks so you can have the calm mind but
if it still
prefers sensuality as the means of
pleasure the animal you still liable to
it
so you need to calm it but not for its
own sake but only for the sake to be
able to start talking to it and
conveying that it should not want it
either it's better for it to not want
it and same with your
will and at the principle
of with drawing from a degree of the
assumed extent of the assumed external
is the
same just obviously on a sub level
but you need to stop acting externally
thinking towards external s sounds smelt
this touches as the cause and the reason
of your sensuality as the cause and
reason of your real
will and if you don't you're just doing
it for yourself you not even seeing the
mind in relation to these two
facts and what is the what is the
message you want to convey to the Mind
regarding ill
will so he drops it so he doesn't want
it so he stops going towards
it we talked about cality and everything
else but how about your
well you know it's bad you know it's
sful but the animal still leans towards
it every now and then when it's
annoyed so how do you teach it not
to remember we spoke about the
reward when the animal does the right
thing on account of you showing it I
want to reward it so it starts doing it
by itself same with the dog training
don't want to always have to guide it no
you want it to do it on its own that's
how it learns okay
so your behavior is the guidance but
it's still not doing on its own so what
is the message you want to convey so it
starts doing on its own so he starts to
prefer it to prefer the non- anger over
anger the same sense he would prefer
anunciation of
sensuality what's the message in
relation to anger specifically do you
want to be happy in the
life okay yeah when you're angry are you
happy yeah yes exactly no that's the
question you should be asking it cuz
that's the point the sole reason for the
anger is to get back onto the happiness
to get back onto the
satisfaction so when he gets angry when
he gets
Disturbed it doesn't know that it
doesn't have to go through the motions
of expressing anger and acting out to
get where it wants to be from the start
all he needs to do is oh I don't want to
I won't be angry and it back where you
want to be from the
start the verse from the
D aversion cannot be dispelled by a by
by a virgin it can only be dispelled by
non a virgin yeah but yeah that's
basically in in in heart of every every
anger or
irritation it's that pressure from from
the animal because it doesn't know that
actually there and then it has the
option to be free from it instantly
that's why anger is quick dispelled as
the Su says Blame blame worthy but
quickly dispelled so it's the same essential to
dispelled so it's the same essential to
be you're dropping
the wanting of this thing cuz if you
don't want
it where's the pressure there so
dropping the not
wanting of this pressure it's irrit you
irritating pressure then you're no pressure there's
pressure then you're no pressure there's
no resistance to it yeah there's no
resistance to he's just with anger you
get almost instantly yeah verified
effort which inity you
don't that's why cality is not
blameworthy but a lot harder to give
up is is what is
describe so in the sense of like say
somebody makes you
angry somebody insults you well they
don't make you angry they insult you
they do something to you get angry on
account of it so somebody this respects
you and now you have all these options
of how you would deal with
that they would obviously require that
person or even more people and so on and
use this and that to address it never
happens again so it's corrected so they
know their mistake all of that but
obviously that would be exactly on the
level of okay so the anger you believe
the anger came from over there so that's
how you're going to treat this condition
by talking about it and sharing your
feelings and making everything known how
you feel inside to everybody well that
will work only for how long till
somebody forgets or until you are in a
bad mood and then start interpreting
everything is disrespect because of your
own insecurity but instead say somebody
insecurity but instead say somebody
intentionally disrespects you it's not
even accidental and as I said you have an
accidental and as I said you have an
option to take on now that burden of
dealing with this or to say okay I do
not have to deal with this person ever
again for the rest of my life and isn't
that a wonderful feel like completely
elevated any burden any sense no hatred
no love either but certainly there is no
reason for hatred because there is
there's nothing I'm trying to express or
deal with it's like you're not my
problem anymore thank you actually I
like you for that now I have no sense of
Duty towards you cuz you didn't earn
it and that's same when the Buddha went
to
the well the gift yeah yeah exactly but
no I meant the C when they were
quarreling when he said stop quarreling
it's you know you're incurring a lot of
demerit and he says well mind your own
business basically it's our demerit not
your demerit and then he told him three
times and three times they dismissed him
he was like okay this foolish man and he
went off and you think like oh so he was
off and you think like oh so he was
completely
disrespected and what did he do just
great I don't have to deal with these
idiots it's like not my problem but then
when s came back and started come on
let's let's go back and help them he did
he wasn't angry with them no well now I
won't go because they offended
me no they said oh you know they were
obviously lost perspective it's for
their Weare let's do it okay let's do it
I don't but either way basically by
people people um by disrespect
by any any kind of abuse directed at you
that in itself automatically reminds you
how free you are from
them and that's the gift Su when he's
throwing insults at him he says oh let
me give an example if you give gifts and
they don't accept the who like I can't
accept it it's not I don't I don't want
I can't I'm unable to accept what you're
given me who does that stay with with
you that entire experience stays with
you does not become my problem all
because ch has been taught to recognize
that very thing which didn't recognize
before which is why the whole pressure
and then you couldn't stop thinking
about it and in Winding yourself up more
and more and more and
more no one can make you angry no one
can make you
angry and people trying to make you
angry but then make you even less
angry more un
angry because nobody ever could make you
angry no no of course
so there a pressure towards anger you
realize okay not expressing it not
giving into it not acting out of it and
then conveying the message to that
actually just try it just just you know
humor me for a second drop it and you'll
see that's what you wanted from the
start when you wanted to go through the
anger every time you did in the
past and actually it's the same for
sensuality as
well the outcome of it is what you want
and you can actually have more direct
access to it by dropping
sensuality that's that the monk we said
to the
DEA when he said like oh why are you
forsaking what's visible here and now
for some uncertain goal later he's like
no what are you talking about it's other
way around I am practicing what's
accessible here and now instead of the
uncertain results later which is
sensuality is always uncertain implies
the time implies the the sequence
implies the uncertainty giving it up
immediately there and then gives you the
satisfaction you wanted through it